Leah: So, what are the
functional and practical
benefits of using pure functions?
Let’s have a look at these in more detail.
Jack: Pure functions are easier to
read as they are self-contained,
as all inputs and dependencies
are provided within the function.
To understand the function, you do
not have to look through the code
for variables which are affected by
the function call, like you might
have to with an impure function.
Leah: The same function can be reused
in different contexts as it only depends
on what occurs inside the function.
In contrast, you might have to
write a separate ‘impure function’
for each global variable that is
changed, rather than relying on pure
functions which do not access these.
Jack: Pure functions have no side
effects, making them much easier to test.
We only need to check the state of
internal variables, not global variables.
Referential transparency.
Leah: When testing a program, the more
processes that run, the longer it takes.
You might want to test a program
but not run certain resource-heavy
functions which make it take longer.
Referential transparency is when you
can replace a function with whatever the
output would , without making any other
parts of the program run differently.
This compiles faster
and helps readability.
Jack: Caching refers to using techniques
to store results of functions, so
they only need to be calculated once.
As pure function’s outputs are
always constant, caching is
possible with pure functions.